English Translation
كوكبة قرية سورية جميلة، تقع جنوب غرب مدينة عفرين في ريف حلب
الشمالي بـ 9 كيلومترات وتتبع لها.
English Translation
Kawkabeh is a beautiful Syrian village, located 9 kilometers
southwest of the city of Afrin in the northern countryside
of Aleppo, and belongs to it.
English Translation
كما أنها تقع إلى الشمال الغربي من مدينة حلب بـ 70 كيلومتراً.
It is also located 70 kilometers northwest of the city of
Aleppo.
English Translation
وتقع على يسار الطريق الواصل بين مدينتي عفرين وناحية جنديرس.
It lies to the left of the road connecting the cities of
Afrin and the Jindires district.
English Translation
يتبع لهذه القرية أربع مزارع، هي بوزيكا، والعجلان، وعكاش،
وحسون.
English Translation
Four farms belong to this village, which are Buzika, Al-
Ajlan, Akash, and Hassoun.
English Translation
إلى الغرب منها تقع قرية كفر بطرة، وإلى الشرق قرية الباسوطة،
ونهر عفرين، ومدينة عفرين.
English Translation
To its west lies the village of Kafr Batra, and to the east
the village of Al-Basouta, the Afrin River, and the city of
Afrin.
English Translation
أما جنوباً، فكفر زيت، وكفيرة، وتلف، وشمالاً مزرعة بوزيكا.
To the south, Kafr Zeit, Kfeirah, and Tleif, and to the
north, the Buzika farm.
English Translation
تبلغ مساحة القرية 1500 هكتار، مزروعة بأشجار الزيتون،
والرمان، والخضراوات، والحبوب.
English Translation
The area of the village is 1500 hectares, planted with olive
trees, pomegranates, vegetables, and grains.
English Translation
يسكن فيها حالياً حوالي 150 عائلة من سكانها الأصليين، ومن
عوائل سورية مهجرة من مناطق سورية مختلفة.
English Translation
Currently, about 150 families of its original inhabitants
live there, along with displaced Syrian families from
different Syrian regions.
English Translation
يوجد في القرية مدرسة ابتدائية وحيدة يعود تاريخ إنشائها إلى
عام 1972.
English Translation
There is only one primary school in the village, dating back
to 1972.
English Translation
يتميز أهالي القرية بالبساطة والطيبة والطبيعة الريفية وأيضاً
بالكرم والشجاعة.
English Translation
The people of the village are characterized by simplicity,
kindness, rural nature, and also by generosity and courage.
English Translation
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
English Translation
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
English Translation
فينا نحكي شوي هيك؟
Can we talk a little?
English Translation
تفضل.
Go ahead.
English Translation
شرف لهون لو سمحت.
Please come here.
English Translation
شلونك؟
How are you?
English Translation
هلا حياك الله.
Welcome, may God bless you.
English Translation
نتعرف عليك؟
Can we know your name?
English Translation
صالح حمادة.
Saleh Hamada.
English Translation
أهلا وسهلا فيك.
Welcome.
English Translation
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
English Translation
من الضيعة ولا مهجر؟
Are you from the village or displaced?
English Translation
لا مهجر.
No, displaced.
English Translation
من وين؟
From where?
English Translation
من حماة.
From Hama.
English Translation
يا أهلا وسهلا.
You are very welcome.
English Translation
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
English Translation
شلون أوضاع المهجرين هون؟
How are the conditions for the displaced people here?
English Translation
والله داحج.
Well, you see.
English Translation
نشتغل..
We work...
English Translation
بالشغل وبالغنم، وغنم داحج ذابحها الجوع، ذابحها ودها أدوية،
ودها كل شيء.
English Translation
With work and sheep, and the sheep, look, hunger is killing
them, they need medicine, they need everything.
English Translation
الله يرزقكم.
May God provide for you.
English Translation
والله شف عينك.
Well, you can see for yourself.
English Translation
ايش بتشتغلوا هون أنتم بالضيعة؟
What do you work in here in the village?
English Translation
والله نشتغل عمال، وناس رعيان.
We work as laborers, and some as shepherds.
English Translation
وهاي هي.
And that's it.
English Translation
معكم أغنام أنتم إلكم؟
Do you have your own sheep?
English Translation
والله ما عندنا.
No, we don't have any.
English Translation
أبدا.
Not at all.
English Translation
أبدا.
Not at all.
English Translation
لكن إيش عم بتشتغل رعوي هون؟
So what are you doing as a shepherd here?
English Translation
أشتغل عامل، وولدي سارح بالغنم عند ناس.
I work as a laborer, and my son is shepherding other
people's sheep.
English Translation
إي.
Yes.
English Translation
بس.
That's all.
English Translation
هلا أنت بمحل، محل ابنك هلق؟
Are you taking your son's place right now?
English Translation
إي محل ابني.
Yes, in my son's place.
English Translation
احكي لي عن وضع الحيوانات.
Tell me about the condition of the animals.
English Translation
والله الحيوانات داحج تموت من الجوع.
Well, the animals are dying of hunger, you see.
English Translation
بدها أدوية، وجوع، بدها علف، ودها تبن.
They need medicine, they are hungry, they need fodder, they
need straw.
English Translation
طيب شرف لهون شوي.
Well, step this way a little.
English Translation
بس يعني أنا مع، في شغلة يعني لفتت نظري.
But, I mean, there's something that caught my attention.
English Translation
يعني كل هالخضار...
I mean, all these greens...
English Translation
إي.
Yes.
English Translation
كل هالرزق، وهي المي ما شاء الله قناة الري، ويعني ما معقول
يكون في جوع.
English Translation
All this bounty, and here is water, mashallah, the
irrigation canal, I mean it's unbelievable there is hunger.
English Translation
والله في جوع، ما في شيء، هلق هاي الرزق لسه توه ما استوت
الأراضي.
English Translation
By God, there is hunger, there is nothing. Right now, this
crop hasn't ripened yet in the lands.
English Translation
السبب ليش أنه ما في مراعي؟
The reason is because there are no pastures?
English Translation
ما في مراعي.
There are no pastures.
English Translation
طيب شو الحل؟
So what's the solution?
English Translation
الحل والله بدها علف.
The solution, by God, is that they need fodder.
English Translation
بدها أدوية، بدها كل شيء، الغنم داحج، داحج تموت منها.
They need medicine, they need everything. The sheep, look,
they are dying from it.
English Translation
ما في منظمات؟
Are there no organizations?
English Translation
ما هو منظمات والله ولا شيء.
There are no organizations, nothing.
English Translation
لكن يعني سعر كمان الحليب كويس، وسعر الغنم...
But the price of milk is also good, and the price of
sheep...
English Translation
والله سعر اللبن والجبن...
Well, the price of yogurt and cheese...
English Translation
من الجوع ما في حليب.
Due to hunger, there is no milk.
English Translation
مغرزة خالص.
They are completely dried up.
English Translation
قاطع الحليب.
They stopped giving milk.
English Translation
قاطع الحليب.
They stopped giving milk.
English Translation
هلق بهذا الوقت ايش بكون، هلق هدول خرفان مو هيك؟
So at this time, what is... these are ewes, right?
English Translation
خرفان إي.
Yes, ewes.
English Translation
هلق بهذا الوقت إيش بكون وضع الأغنام يعني؟ هل بتكون مثلاً
حامل، بتكون قربت تولد، إيش هو؟
English Translation
At this time, what is the condition of the sheep? Are they
pregnant, for example? Are they about to give birth? What is
it?
English Translation
والله بدها يعني شهر، شهرين بدها تولد.
Well, they need a month or two to give birth.
English Translation
إي بس بدها علف الغنم ما فيها حليب هلق، إذا ولدت بده يموت
الطلي الجنين، ما في حليب.
English Translation
Yes, but they need fodder. The sheep have no milk right now.
If they give birth, the lamb will die. There's no milk.
English Translation
طيب هلق أول وين كان يرعوا أول لكان؟
So where did they used to graze before then?
English Translation
قبل كنا نرعى حبة سودة، كل من فلحوها وزرعوها خضار.
Before, we used to graze them on black cumin, but they
plowed it and planted vegetables.
English Translation
فلحوها، كانت حبة سودة من فترة؟
They plowed it. There was black cumin a while ago?
English Translation
إي من فترة حبة سودة...
Yes, a while ago there was black cumin...
English Translation
بين الزيتون؟
Between the olive trees?
English Translation
بين الزيتون...
Between the olive trees...
English Translation
إي من خلصت فلحوها، وخلصوا، فلحوها الدار داحج تراب أحمر.
Yes, when it finished, they plowed it, and they finished,
they plowed the land, look, it's red dirt.
English Translation
وزيتون حامل ما بنسرح فيه، حطينا بهالجبل، الغنم ضاوية.
And the olive trees are bearing fruit, we don't graze them
there. We put them in this mountain, the sheep are weak.
English Translation
ما جبتوا تبن ما اشتريتوا تبن؟
Didn't you bring straw? Didn't you buy straw?
English Translation
منين غلات والله ما عندنا مصاري منين،
It's expensive, by God, we don't have money, from where?
English Translation
قديش اليوم كيلو التبن؟
How much is a kilo of straw today?
English Translation
والله ما أعرف، 200، 300 والله ما بعرف ما اشترينا، ما عندنا،
يعني ما تنباع معنا الحلال لنشتري تبن.
English Translation
By God, I don't know, 200, 300, by God, I don't know. We
didn't buy, we don't have, I mean, the livestock doesn't
sell for us to buy straw.
English Translation
ما في، يعني داحج تموت والله من الجوع حتى الخرفان.
There's nothing, I mean look, they are literally dying of
hunger, even the lambs.
English Translation
حسبي الله ونعم الوكيل.
God is sufficient for us, and He is the best disposer of
affairs.
English Translation
حسبي الله ونعم الوكيل.
God is sufficient for us, and He is the best disposer of
affairs.
English Translation
لا أدوية، لا شيء، لا شياتين ولا شيء.
No medicine, no nothing, no things at all.
English Translation
ما فكرتوا تنقلوا فيها برا كوكبة، برا الضيعة؟
Haven't you thought of moving them outside Kawkabeh, outside
the village?
English Translation
والله ما في شيء، كلها ممحلة ما فيها شيء.
By God, there's nothing, it's all barren, there's nothing.
English Translation
أبدا؟
Not at all?
English Translation
أبداً.
Not at all.
English Translation
هلق على أطراف السواقي...
What about on the edges of the streams...
English Translation
ما والله أطراف النهر...
No, by God, the edges of the river...
English Translation
والله ما فيها شيء.
By God, there's nothing there.
English Translation
ما فيها شيء والله.
There is nothing there, by God.
English Translation
والله ما في، كلها حاطينها بهالعوش ضاوية والغنم حاطينها
بالجبل ضاوية.
English Translation
By God, there is nothing, they put them all in these barns
weak, and they put the sheep in the mountain weak.
English Translation
بالجبل وين؟
Where in the mountain?
English Translation
طالعين فوق الجبل، هلق شرقي كوكبة، حاطين هناك ضاوية.
They go up the mountain, east of Kawkabeh, they put them
there weak.
English Translation
بتضل للمغرب لنجيبها؟
They stay until sunset before you bring them back?
English Translation
إي ضال للمغرب ونجيبها، ونحطها بالحبوس هاي.
Yes, they stay until sunset and we bring them back, and put
them in these pens.
English Translation
ايش ترعى هنيك؟
What do they graze on there?
English Translation
والله ما بترعى شيء، بس عالحرف هالنهر نوبات زل من هالشوك.
By God, they graze on nothing, just by the riverbank
sometimes there are some reeds and thorns.
English Translation
يعني معناها مشكلة الثروة الحيوانية والأغنام هون فيها مشكلة؟
So this means the problem of livestock and sheep here is a
real problem?
English Translation
تحت الصفر.
Below zero.
English Translation
تحت الصفر.
Below zero.
English Translation
هلا الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
English Translation
الله يعافيك أهلاً وسهلاً أهلاً وسهلاً.
May God give you health, welcome, welcome.
English Translation
الله يرزقكم.
May God provide for you.
English Translation
الله يسلمك يا أستاذنا مع السلامة هلا.
May God keep you safe, sir, goodbye now.
English Translation
كوكبة قرية صغيرة كتير وتاريخها ما هو بعيد كتير.
Kawkabeh is a very small village and its history is not that
old.
English Translation
المعروف عن تاريخها بأنه عشيرتين هنن العجلان والعميرات
العربيتين، هنن اللي الان ساكنين هالقرية ويمكن عمرهم بيوصل
بين 150 لـ 200 سنة بهالقرية.
English Translation
What is known about its history is that there are two Arab
tribes, the Al-Ajlan and Al-Omairat, who currently inhabit
this village, and their age in this village could reach
between 150 to 200 years.
English Translation
لنعرف اكتر عن تاريخ قرية كوكبة راح يكون معنا الأستاذ جمال
عبد المحمد، أحد أبناء القرية والمهتمين بتاريخها.
English Translation
To learn more about the history of Kawkabeh village, we will
have with us Mr. Jamal Abd Al-Muhammad, one of the village's
sons who is interested in its history.
English Translation
يعطيك العافية أستاذ جمال.
May God give you health, Mr. Jamal.
English Translation
أهلاً وسهلاً الله يعافيك الله يخليك.
Welcome, may God give you health and keep you safe.
English Translation
بدي اسألك، خلينا نمشي شوي.
I want to ask you, let's walk a bit.
English Translation
نعم.
Yes.
English Translation
أبعد تاريخ لكوكبة لما صارت تجمع بشري وصار اسمها قرية، ايمت؟
What is the earliest date for Kawkabeh when it became a
human settlement and got named a village, when?
English Translation
والله أنا بقول على الأقل 150 سنة.
Well, I say at least 150 years.
English Translation
ليش؟
Why?
English Translation
لأنه في يعني أجدادنا يعني كانوا يحكوا لنا.
Because, our grandfathers used to tell us.
English Translation
وكانوا يعني عمرهم يعني هلق صار لهم ميتين من 20 و30 و35 سنة،
ومنهم عاشوا 110 و120 سنة وأبهاتهم لسه كانوا موجودين يعني.
English Translation
And they were, their ages were, well they passed away 20,
30, and 35 years ago, and some of them lived for 110 and 120
years, and their fathers were still around then.
English Translation
لذلك أنت بتقول 150 سنة؟
That's why you say 150 years?
English Translation
أنا بقول على الأقل يعني، مو بالدقة يعني بجوز أكثر يعني.
I say at least, not exactly, maybe more.
English Translation
طيب تاريخيا.
Well historically.
English Translation
نعم.
Yes.
English Translation
قبل ما يجوا أجدادكم لهون العجلان والعميرات...
Before your ancestors from Al-Ajlan and Al-Omairat came
here...
English Translation
نعم.
Yes.
English Translation
كان في هون شي بناء، كان في قرية، كان في شي؟
Was there any building here? Was there a village? Was there
anything?
English Translation
لا، كان يعني الأراضي الزراعية ما بعرف يعني انه البيت الأول
كان يعني بالضيعة، القرية كان يعني للاغوات، البكوات يعني.
English Translation
No, it was just agricultural lands, I don't know, the first
house in the village, the village belonged to the Aghas, the
Beys, you know.
English Translation
نعم.
Yes.
English Translation
قبلهم كانوا الصفونات وكانوا يملكوا الأراضي هدول، وبعدين
باعوها...
English Translation
Before them, it was the Saffounat, and they used to own
these lands, and then they sold them...
English Translation
مين الصفونات، مين الأغوات، عشان يعرفوا المشاهدين؟
Who are the Saffounat, who are the Aghas, so the viewers can
know?
English Translation
الصفونات هني عائلة كردية، يعني لا زالت موجودة بعض منها يمكن
بعفرين أو هيك يعني.
English Translation
The Saffounat are a Kurdish family, some of them might still
be in Afrin or something like that.
English Translation
نعم، أيوه، هني ملاك الأرض الأصليين هون؟
Yes, I see, they are the original landowners here?
English Translation
هني مالكين يعني كانوا كل الأرض أو نصها يعني، كانوا مالكين
هون بشكل كبير يعني.
English Translation
They were the owners, they owned all the land or half of it,
they owned a large part of it here.
English Translation
وبعدين باعوها لبيت قاسم بيك، الحلبية يعني من حلب.
And then they sold it to the Qasim Bey family, the Halabiya
from Aleppo.
English Translation
وبعدين قاسم بيك باع لأرمن، قسم منها، وقسم...
And then Qasim Bey sold it to the Armenians, a part of it,
and a part...
English Translation
آغوب كشيشيان.
Agop Keshishian.
English Translation
إي آغوب كشيشيان، تماما.
Yes, Agop Keshishian, exactly.
English Translation
نعم.
Yes.
English Translation
هالحكي كلياته ايمت صار؟
When did all this happen?
English Translation
يعني بين الصفونات وبين قاسم بيك، وآغوب كشيشيان.
I mean between the Saffounat, Qasim Bey, and Agop
Keshishian.
English Translation
والله أنا بقول...
Well, I say...
English Translation
لايمت يعني، ايمت مرحلتهم انتهت؟
Until when? I mean, when did their phase end?
English Translation
والله أنا بقول انتهت بحدود يعني الستينات يعني، أو يعني، لانه
مرات كل مرحلة لها مثلا 30، 40، 50 سنة يعني هيك يعني.
English Translation
Well, I say it ended around the sixties, or, you know,
because sometimes each phase lasts for maybe 30, 40, or 50
years, like that.
English Translation
تمام.
Exactly.
English Translation
إي.
Yes.
English Translation
صارت الأرض مع آغوب كشيشيان،
The land went to Agop Keshishian.
English Translation
نعم.
Yes.
English Translation
اللي هو دخل لهون البذارات القمح، ومو هيك؟
Who brought the wheat seeders here, right?
English Translation
طبعاً، هو كان يعني رجل عشان ما يعني نعطي كل واحد حقه انه
يعني مبدع كان يعني بالزراعة، وبال.. هو متل ما قلت دخل
البذارات والنثارات تبع الأسمدة للمنطقة، ويمكن لمحافظة حلب
ومن ثَمّ لكل سوريا يعني.
English Translation
Of course, he was a man, to give everyone their due, he was
innovative in agriculture, and in... as you said, he
introduced seeders and fertilizer spreaders to the region,
and maybe to the Aleppo governorate and then to all of
Syria.
English Translation
نعم.
Yes.
English Translation
هلق بعد آغوب كشيشيان، أنتم ايمت جيتوا لهون، أنتم كعشيرة
العميرات؟
English Translation
Now after Agop Keshishian, when did you guys come here, as
the Al-Omairat tribe?
English Translation
ايمت جيتوا عالضيعة؟
When did you come to the village?
English Translation
نحن كمان موجودين، كانوا قسم يعمل مثلاً عند هالعالم و...
We were also around, a part of us worked, for example, for
these people and...
English Translation
كمزارعين؟
As farmers?
English Translation
إي طبعا بالزراعة ووكلاء وهيك.
Yes, of course, in agriculture, as agents, and so on.
English Translation
وقسم كان يعني يعمل بالرعية وهيك يلحق الغنم والماشية يعني.
And a part of us worked in shepherding and such, following
the sheep and livestock.
English Translation
نعم.
Yes.
English Translation
عهالأساس يعني ظلينا بالخمسين... يعني أنا مثلا مواليد 72،
والدي يعني ما قبله يعني، في ناس مواليد الضيعة يعني.
English Translation
Based on that, we stayed in the fifties... I mean, for
example, I was born in 72, my father and those before him,
there are people born in the village.
English Translation
إي.
Yes.
English Translation
بأي سنة أنتم استملكتوا هون الأراضي؟
In what year did you take ownership of the lands here?
English Translation
والله نحن اشترينا قسم، وجاء الإصلاح الزراعي كمان يعني، أعطى
للناس قسم...
English Translation
Well, we bought a part, and the agrarian reform came too, it
gave people a part...
English Translation
بأي سنة؟
In what year?
English Translation
بال.. لازم 63، 64.
In.. it must be 63, 64.
English Translation
يعني أنتم اشتريتوا قسم من آغوب كشيشيان، ومن.. من.. ورثة قاسم
بيك؟
English Translation
Meaning you bought a part from Agop Keshishian, and from..
from.. the heirs of Qasim Bey?
English Translation
اشترينا قسم.
We bought a part.
English Translation
ورثت قاسم بيك.
The heirs of Qasim Bey.
English Translation
نعم.
Yes.
English Translation
وقسم آخر توزع عليكم كإصلاح زراعي؟
And another part was distributed to you as agrarian reform?
English Translation
قسم آخر توزع علينا من الإصلاح الزراعي.
Another part was distributed to us from the agrarian reform.
English Translation
شرف.
Step this way.
English Translation
طبعاً حضرتك يعني كفيف،
Of course, sir, you are blind.
English Translation
نعم.
Yes.
English Translation
لذلك يعني عم نمشي بهي الطريقة بسهولة أو عفوا ببطء لحتى نقدر
نوصل.
English Translation
That's why we are walking this way easily or sorry slowly so
we can get there.
English Translation
الله يكرمك.
May God honor you.
English Translation
الله يكرمك، طبعاً أنت كفيف ولادياً؟
May God honor you, of course you are blind from birth?
English Translation
ولادياً.
From birth.
English Translation
نعم، ولكن ما شاء الله عندك معلومات قيمة.
Yes, but mashallah you have valuable information.
English Translation
الحمد لله رب العالمين.
Praise be to God Almighty.
English Translation
إذا الله أخذ البصر، عطى البصيرة.
If God took away the sight, He gave the insight.
English Translation
إن شاء الله تعالى، إن شاء الله تعالى.
God willing, God willing.
English Translation
العجلان كانوا قبلكم ولا أنتم العميرات؟
Were the Al-Ajlan here before you or you the Al-Omairat?
English Translation
والله العميرات موجودين، والعجلان كمان موجودين يعني.
Well, the Al-Omairat are around, and the Al-Ajlan are also
around.
English Translation
نفس الفترة؟
At the same time?
English Translation
والله بجوز يعني العميرات قبل...
Well, maybe the Al-Omairat were before...
English Translation
أو قريبة من بعضها، هن كمان قديمين، يعني أنا اللي ما بذكره،
هدول جواريننا من زمان يعني...
English Translation
Or close to each other, they are also old, I mean what I
remember is that these are our neighbors from a long time
ago...
English Translation
يعني من بذكر انه هالناس موجودين و... يعني عايشين حالة توأمة
يعني بين بعضنا، الحمد لله يعني.
English Translation
I mean since I can remember, these people are around and...
we live like twins with each other, thank God.
English Translation
كيف كانت يعني علاقة كوكبة مع القرى المجاورة كمنطقة عفرين؟
How was the relationship of Kawkabeh with the neighboring
villages in the Afrin region?
English Translation
والله تمام، الحمد لله، كلها في صداقات وفي كذا، وأي خلاف
تتدخل وجهاء العشائر وتحله.
English Translation
Well, perfect, thank God. It's all friendships and such, and
if there is any dispute, the tribal leaders intervene and
solve it.
English Translation
يعني الحمد لله، ما في أي مشكلة، ما.. الحمد لله العلاقة جيدة
جدا يعني.
English Translation
So thank God, there is no problem at all, thank God the
relationship is very good.
English Translation
اللهجة واللغة اللي بتحكوها هون هي اللهجة...
The dialect and language you speak here is the dialect...
هي لهجة بدوية ولا اللهجة خلينا نسميها الحضرية ولا لغة كردية
ولا شو؟
Is this a Bedouin dialect, or let's call it an urban
dialect, or a Kurdish language, or what?
نحن اللهجة اللي نحكيها هي اللهجة اللي عم احكيك بيها الآن
يعني، هي لهجة بدوية بحتة يعني.
The dialect we speak is the one I am speaking to you with
now, it is a pure Bedouin dialect.
اللغة الكردية عند الكبار يعني بيعرفوا منهم قليل، لكن الجيل
هاد يعني من 50 سنة وما دون قليل كلمات كذا هيك يعني.
As for the Kurdish language, a few of the elders know it,
but this generation, from 50 years and under, only know a
few words here and there.
كوكبة ما حدا بيعرف بالكردي، لكن عند عامة العميرات بمنطقة
عفرين اللغة الكردية بيحكوها كلغة ثانية.
In Kawkabeh, no one knows Kurdish, but among the general
Amirat tribe in the Afrin region, they speak Kurdish as a
second language.
يعني بيعرفوا يحكوا كردي تمام.
They know how to speak Kurdish perfectly.
تمام. من وين اجا اسم كوكبة؟
Great. Where did the name Kawkabeh come from?
والله أنا حكى لي رجل عمره يعني هداك الوقت شي 70 سنة، هالحكي
من حوالي الـ 35 - 40 سنة، هو من بيت عباس هذول العجلان.
Well, a man who was about 70 years old at the time told me,
this was about 35 to 40 years ago, he's from the Abbas
family, the Ajlan.
قال لي أنت بتعرف ليش هي اسمها كوكبة؟ قلت له لا والله. قال لي
إنه هي كانت بنت...
He said to me, 'Do you know why it's called Kawkabeh?' I
said, 'No, by God.' He told me that there was a girl...
يعني حبت شخص، وهالبنت اسمها كوكب.
...who loved a person, and this girl was named Kawkab.
من الضيعة؟
From the village?
من الضيعة يعني.
From the village, yes.
وهالبنت هي يعني لما راح الشب بده يخطبها، أبوها أعطاه شروط
تعجيزية، إنه بدك تفتح طريق من هون لما بعرف وين.
And this girl, when the young man went to ask for her hand
in marriage, her father gave him impossible conditions, like
you have to open a road from here to I don't know where.
وبدك تساوي وبدك كذا، فهي البنت حزنت كتير، وماتت واندفنت هون،
وصاروا يقولوا كوكبة، كوكب، هي كوكب، كوكب، كوكبة...
And you have to do this and that. So the girl became very
sad, she died and was buried here, and they started saying
Kawkabeh, Kawkab, she is Kawkab, Kawkab, Kawkabeh...
محل ما اندفنت يعني، وصارت الضيعة يعني. هيك على ما يروى يعني.
...where she was buried, and it became the village. That is
as the story goes.
هيك على ما يروى إنه بهذا الشكل.
As the story goes, it happened like this.
في سؤال أخير، كوكبة قرية وإلها مزارع، شو اسم المزارع؟
One last question: Kawkabeh is a village and has farms, what
are the names of the farms?
والله المزارع، في مزرعة حسون شماليتها...
Well, the farms, there is Hassoun farm to its north...
في بوزيكة، في العكاشين، في مزرعة العجلان اللي هي جنوب
الضيعة.
...there is Bouzika, there is Al-Akashin, and there is Al-
Ajlan farm, which is south of the village.
أربع مزارع يعني؟
Four farms, then?
إيه أربع مزارع تقريبا.
Yes, about four farms.
الله يعطيك العافية، شكرا إلك، شكرا إلك يا أستاذ جمال، الله
يكرمك يا رب.
May God give you health, thank you. Thank you, Mr. Jamal,
may God bless you.
[Music]
تتميز كوكبة عن بقية منطقة عفرين بالأحجار البازلتية البركانية
السوداء الصماء، ولذلك انبنت بيوتها الأولى من زمان بهيدي
الأحجار السوداء.
Kawkabeh is distinguished from the rest of the Afrin region
by its solid black volcanic basalt rocks, and that's why its
first houses were built a long time ago with these black
stones.
واحد من أقدم البيوت اللي بكوكبة هو بيت الآغا. اليوم رح نزور
سكان هالبيت، وهالبيت لنتعرف على أقسامه التاريخية، وعلى
التطوير اللي حصل فيه، والتجديد اللي حصل فيه. تابعونا.
One of the oldest houses in Kawkabeh is the Agha's house.
Today we will visit the residents of this house and the
house itself, to learn about its historical sections, the
development it underwent, and the renovations that took
place. Follow us.
أبو علي! السلام عليكم.
Abu Ali! Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام، سلامات أهلا أستاذ.
And upon you be peace, greetings, welcome, sir.
شلونك؟
How are you?
حياك الله.
May God bless you.
هلق هذا البيت اللي أنتم ساكنين فيه حاليا، هذا كان بيت الآغا.
أين هو القسم القديم هون؟ أنا شايف ثلاث أقسام، واحد، اثنين،
ثلاثة.
Now, this house that you currently live in, this was the
Agha's house. Where is the old section here? I see three
sections: one, two, three.
القسم القديم هاد هو.
This is the old section.
نعم.
Yes.
هاد هو القسم القديم.
This is the old section.
هاد المعمر بالأحجار السوداء البازلتية؟
This one built with black basalt stones?
إيه هاد تقريبا البيت عمره أكثر من 100 سنة يعني.
Yes, this house is probably more than 100 years old.
100 سنة؟
100 years?
إيه.
Yes.
هاد على دور البكوات أولي، والوالد الله يرحمه اشتراه وصار
قديم هالحكي هاد.
This was from the time of the Beys originally, and my late
father bought it a long time ago.
طيب بس خلينا نوقف هيك عشان تبين ورانا البيت.
Okay, let's just stand like this so the house shows behind
us.
هلق هاد البيت كم كم غرفة؟ هذا القسم.
Now, how many rooms is this house? This section.
هذا ثلاث غرف.
This one has three rooms.
ثلاث غرف؟ مبين علي اثنين بس.
Three rooms? I only see two.
غرفة وفي وحدة داخلية صايرة، وهي غرفة تانية.
A room, and there's an internal one, and this is another
room.
خلينا نقرب شوي لهون، تفضل.
Let's get a bit closer here, go ahead.
هلق أنا شايف سقفه سقف عادي هون، ولا هو كان مصلب؟
Now, I see its roof is a regular roof here, or was it cross-
vaulted?
لا بالنسبة للبيت أولي كان كله ترابي. شوية تحدث على دور
أبهاتنا.
No, as for the house, originally it was all dirt. It was
modernized a bit during our fathers' time.
سووه صبوه بيتون وما بيتون.
They poured concrete and so on.
عم تحكي عن السقف. لكن الحجر البناء هذا هو الأصلي؟
You're talking about the roof. But the stone building, is
this the original?
البناء، تقريبا شيء بسيط أحدثوا، كان تراب هاد.
The building, they updated it slightly, this was dirt.
دخلوا فيه شوي أسمنت وما أسمنت.
They put some cement and stuff in it.
يعني كان حجر أسود وتراب؟
So it was black stone and dirt?
حجر أسود وتراب.
Black stone and dirt.
صار أسمنت؟
It became cement?
صار أسمنت.
It became cement.
تمام، وهون كان هون كان السقف ترابي؟
Great, and here the roof was dirt?
السقف ترابي. ومصلبات، هدول في قناطر صاير بيناتهم.
The roof was dirt. And cross vaults, there are arches
between them.
أيوا قناطر هون.
Ah, arches here.
إيه أربع قناطر، ويتقسم في على غرفة تانية، هي متل غرفة نوم
أولي قديمة يعني تعتبر.
Yes, four arches, and it is divided into another room, this
is like an old bedroom originally, it is considered.
غرفة غرفة الضيوف؟
A guest room?
لا هي تبع ضيوف، هون تعتبر غرفة نوم وهون في غرفة تابعة إلها
كمان، غرفة معيشة.
No, this one is for guests, here is considered a bedroom,
and here is a room attached to it too, a living room.
وهذا العمود بالأصل موجود هيك؟
And was this column originally like this?
إيه موجود هذا العمود.
Yes, this column was there.
وكان هون في قناطر بس أنتو شلتوا السقف الترابي مو القناطر،
وسويتوها بيتون؟
And there were arches here, but you removed the dirt roof,
not the arches, and made it concrete?
أيوا بالضبط.
Yes, exactly.
على دور أبوي الله يرحمه سقفوا، صار بيتون. أولي كان كله ترابي
وعمد وما عمد وهيك شغلات يعني.
During my late father's time, they roofed it, it became
concrete. Originally it was all dirt and pillars and stuff
like that.
أوكي تفضل. وهلق نحن في عنا قسمين، عنا هذا القسم وعنا هذا
القسم.
Okay, go ahead. And now we have two sections, we have this
section and we have this section.
طبعا أنت أخي متزوجين ثنتين بس مشان يعرفوا المشاهدين أنت آخذ
نسوان ثنتين.
Of course, my brother, you are married to two, just so the
viewers know, you have two wives.
إيه.
Yes.
ومسكن الجديدة هنيك والقديمة هون.
And you settled the new one there and the old one here.
صح.
Right.
طيب، هذا القسم كمان كان قديم وجددته ولا كيف؟
Okay, was this section also old and you renovated it, or
how?
القسم هاد يا سيدي، كان قديم أقدم من هذا بكثير.
This section, sir, was old, much older than this one.
كله قناطر هذا، كان كله ترابي، وقناطر شبه متل آثار القلعة وما
قلعة يعني كان.
It was all arches, it was all dirt, and arches almost like
the ruins of a castle or something.
طيب.
Okay.
إيه حدثوا على دور أبهاتنا وصار يعني كله عمار وحديث يعني
وصبينا..
Yes, they modernized it during our fathers' time and it
became all building and modern, and we poured...
إيمتى صار التجديد؟
When did the renovation happen?
تقريبا بالـ 91.
Around '91.
بالـ 91. هلق أنا القسم شايفه كتير عندك أول شي أرض الديار
كتير حلوة.
In '91. Now I see the section, first of all, your courtyard
is very beautiful.
تاني شي واضح إنه هون في، في خضار في مياه. من وين المي عندكم؟
البيت هو دارك المؤلفة من ثلاث أقسام فيها خضار وفيها شجر كتير
كويس.
Second, it's clear that here there is greenery, there is
water. Where do you get the water from? The house is your
home, consisting of three sections, it has greenery and very
nice trees.
خيو أول عالدور الأولي كان في نبع فوق الضيعة، والنبع كانت
تيجي لهون ورا البيت.
Well, at first, in the old days, there was a spring above
the village, and the spring used to come here behind the
house.
في هيك متل الحاووز يعني متل بركة المي، شبه بركة، يوردوا هيك
يسقوا الأشجار وما أشجار، ما عرفت علي؟
There was like a reservoir, like a pool of water, almost a
pool, they would come and water the trees and so on, you
know?
صار جفاف صار له كم سنة تقريبا. حفرنا بير عاد من شي تقريبا
بالـ 95، بير مي انقطعت مية النبع انقطعت.
There has been a drought for a few years now. We dug a well
then, around '95, a water well, the spring water got cut
off.
حفرنا بير صارت المي هلق نظامية مية بير نبع نظامية.
We dug a well, now the water is regular, regular spring well
water.
خلينا نوقف هون نوقف هون إيه نطلع شوي لفوق بس.
Let's stand here, stand here, yes, let's go up a bit.
الأشجار اللي عندك، هلق عد لي الأشجار اللي عندك.
The trees you have, now count the trees you have for me.
متل هي دنيا، ليمون، برتقال، مانجا، رمان،
Like this loquat, lemon, orange, mango, pomegranate...
إيه هي شجر عنب.
Yes, this is a grape vine.
وكله ناجح بشكل عام كله ناجح عندكم هون يعني.
And it's all successful? In general, everything is
successful for you here, I mean.
طيب سؤال أخير، البيوت في الضيعة في كوكبة كلها متل بيتك على
هذا نفس البناء يعني نفس النمط إنه البيوت مفتوحة على ساحة؟
Okay, one last question. Are the houses in the village, in
Kawkabeh, all like your house, with this same structure,
meaning the same pattern of houses opening onto a courtyard?
أرض ديار؟ والله الأغلبية لا، يعني الربع تقريبا هيك، وقسم قسم
من الضيعة هيك.
Courtyard? Well, the majority no, maybe a quarter are
roughly like this, a part of the village is like this.
وكل قسم هاد بما إنه بيت قديم صار بيت شبه أثري يعني، ضل على
تركيبته الأصلية بشيء بسيط تتعدل فيه.
And this part, since it is an old house, it became somewhat
like a heritage house, it remained in its original structure
with minor modifications.
تزريقات، عمارات هيك تتعدل، بس أرضية الحوش على قديمة يعني.
Some plastering, buildings like this get modified, but the
courtyard floor is the old one.
أرض الديار هي نفسها.
The courtyard is the same.
إيه.
Yes.
وأنت صرتوا بقى تعمروا أقسام جديدة.
And you started to build new sections.
إيه متل هلق تزفتت أو هيك هي كلها جديدة، كان أولي كله ترابي
وما ترابي.
Yes, like now it got paved or so, this is all new,
originally it was all dirt and so on.
أنت بتمون خضرتك من هون من أرض الدار؟ تزرع شي هيك ولا من
الأرض اللي زارعها؟
Do you supply your vegetables from here, from the courtyard?
Do you plant anything like that, or from the land you
cultivate?
والله هون زارع تحت البيت مباشرة يعني جنب الـ... إيه خضروات
هيك بسيطة.
Well, here I plant directly under the house, I mean next to
the... yes, simple vegetables like this.
والباقي نشتري مشترى من البلد.
And the rest we buy from the town.
شو عندك أولاد الله يخليهم؟
What children do you have, may God protect them?
عندي سبع بنات وولدين.
I have seven daughters and two sons.
الله يخليهم الله يخليهم. الله يعطيك العافية. شكرا إلك.
May God protect them, may God protect them. May God give you
health. Thank you.
حبيبي الله يكرمك أهلا أستاذ سلامات.
My dear, may God bless you. Welcome, sir, greetings.
[Music]
نسبة كبيرة من سكان كوكبة من عشيرة العميرات العربية، اللي اجت
لمنطقة عفرين من فترة زمنية طويلة بحثا عن الكلأ والماء وأيضا
السكن والأمان.
A large percentage of Kawkabeh's residents are from the Arab
Amirat tribe, who came to the Afrin region a long time ago
in search of pasture, water, and also a place to live and
safety.
قدمت لهالمنطقة من الجزيرة السورية. لنحكي أكتر عن عشيرة
العميرات رح يكون معنا العم عبدين كربوج، واحد من سكان كوكبة
واللي بيعرفوا بتاريخ العميرات. يعطيك العافية عمي أبو عبدو.
They came to this region from the Syrian Jazira. To talk
more about the Amirat tribe, we will have Uncle Abdin
Karbouj with us, one of Kawkabeh's residents who is
knowledgeable about the history of the Amirat. May God give
you health, Uncle Abu Abdo.
أهلي وسهلين مية سلامة.
Welcome, a hundred greetings.
الله يسلمك. احكي لي عن العميرات، منين اجوا ويعني شو أصلهم
هون؟
God keep you safe. Tell me about the Amirat, where did they
come from and, I mean, what is their origin here?
اجوا من الجزيرة.
They came from the Jazira.
من وين بالجزيرة؟
Where from in the Jazira?
من صرين وما من عند جسر قره قوزاق أخيوه..
From Sarrin and near the Qara Qozak bridge, my brother...
يعني تابعين لمنبج ولا بعد.
Meaning they belong to Manbij and beyond.
تمام أصل العميرات من وين؟
Great, where are the Amirat originally from?
هو يعني سابقا قديم قديم ما كان أخيو من اليمن.
I mean, in the past, a very long time ago, they were from
Yemen, my brother.
إيه.
Yes.
واجوا من اليمن أخيوه على بلاد الشام هون.
And they came from Yemen, my brother, to the Levant here.
اجوا أخيوه بصرين، واجوا بـ.. يعني حواليها.
They came to Sarrin, my brother, and they came to... meaning
around there.
عشائر عربية اجت بهاي الشام.
Arab tribes that came to the Levant.
أيوة.
Yes.
لمين بينتسبوا؟
Who do they belong to?
بينتسبوا لعشيرة العميرات.
They belong to the Amirat tribe.
العميرات بس هنن هي عشيرة، منين قبيلتهم؟
The Amirat, but they are a clan, what is their tribe?
شيخ البو شعبان.
The Sheikh of Albu Shaban.
البو شعبان؟
Albu Shaban?
البو شعبان.
Albu Shaban.
البو شعبان كم عشيرة؟
How many clans are in Albu Shaban?
34 عشيرة.
34 clans.
والعميرات كم كم فخذ؟
And the Amirat, how many branches?
العميرات 7 أفخاذ.
The Amirat have 7 branches.
فينا نعددهم؟
Can we list them?
العثمان، والفاووت، وحسن داوود، والبوغاز، والمطرد..
Al-Othman, Al-Fawout, Hasan Dawoud, Al-Boughaz, Al-Matrad...
اجوا من الجزيرة من لهون لمنطقة عفرين، ليش اجوا جوا لهون؟ من
إيمتى اجوا؟
They came from the Jazira to here, to the Afrin region, why
did they come here? When did they come?
اجوا من شي 200 سنة.
They came about 200 years ago.
صارت أخيو يعني مشكلة بين أخيو الـ، هدول العفادلة والعميرات،
صارت بلشة وقاموا تهجروا، يعني طفشوا،
There was, my brother, a problem between the Afadla and the
Amirat. A fight started, and they were displaced, I mean
they fled.
قسم أخيو ضل هنيك أخيو بالجزيرة، وقسم اجا لهون لعفرين. الحكي
يمكن من شي 200 سنة هالمشكلة هي صارت.
A part of them stayed there in the Jazira, my brother, and a
part came here to Afrin. This happened maybe about 200 years
ago, this problem.
طيب وين توزعوا بعفرين؟
Okay, where did they distribute themselves in Afrin?
توزعوا أخيو من جبل رجو ومنطقة عفرين، وبالبلد وبهالضيع.
They distributed themselves, my brother, from Mount Rajo and
the Afrin region, in the town and these villages.
أهم الضيع اليوم متواجدين فيها وين؟
The most important villages they are present in today, where
are they?
والله هون كوكبة، وبابليت، وعفرين، وبتيتة، وتل طويل، واصطيرو،
وكفيرة،
Well, here in Kawkabeh, Bableet, Afrin, Bteiteh, Tall Tawil,
Istairo, Kfayreh...
بالشتا براجو حصراً.
In the winter in Rajo, strictly.
ليش براجو حصراً؟
Why strictly in Rajo?
كان هنيك في مغر، وفي أخي مشان يأووا فيها الدواب.
There were caves there, and brother, so they could shelter
the animals in them.
ايمتى لكان كل واحد أو كل فخذ منهم استوطنت في قرية؟
When did each person, or each clan of them, settle in a
village?
مثلاً انتو بكوكبة، وغيركم بباتيتا، ايمتى هالحركة صار انه
استوطنوا؟
For example, you in Kawkaba, and others in Batiyta, when did
this movement happen where they settled?
والله هي، بدك تقول من... بالـ 64 تقريباً.
By God, it was... you could say... around '64.
انتو بالـ 64 هون صرتو في كوكبة؟
In '64 you became here in Kawkaba?
العميرات أخي كلياتها لما أخي هو جمال عبد الناصر قال أخي بدنا
نقطع المعز مشان الحرج وما حرج.
The 'Amirat tribe, brother, all of them when Jamal Abdel
Nasser said we must stop raising goats because of the
forests and so on.
قام أخي بيع العالم الحلال إجباري.
So he made people sell their livestock forcefully.
الأغنام والمعز، أخي بايع، ممنوع بالحرج.
Sheep and goats, brother, sell them, it's forbidden in the
forest.
قاموا أخي هالعرب، أخي العميرات باعوا أخي، اجوا اشتروا أخي
بعفرين.
So these Arabs, the 'Amirat, sold them, came and bought in
Afrin.
وقسم استوطنوا بالضيع، وبركوا.
And a section of them settled in the villages, and stayed.
يعني بقوا حوالي من بداية ما اجوا من الجزيرة، من صرين، من 200
سنة للستينات متنقلين بين راجو وجبل راجو وهالقرى.
So they stayed for about... from when they first came from
the Jazira region, from Sarrin, 200 years ago until the
sixties, moving between Rajo, Mount Rajo, and these
villages.
وهالقرى.
And these villages.
بالستينات استوطنوا في القرى؟
In the sixties, they settled in the villages?
ايوا.
Yes.
الحرج اللي عبد الناصر منع الرعي فيه هو حرج راجو؟
The forest where Abdel Nasser banned grazing, is it the Rajo
forest?
حرج راجو.
Rajo forest.
ايوا، تمام.
I see, okay.
طيب لما استوطنوا في القرى، تغيرت طبيعة حياتهم؟ ولا بقوا
رعيان؟
Well, when they settled in the villages, did the nature of
their lives change? Or did they remain shepherds?
لا ظلوا ساحبين غنم، بس مو هالغنم الكثيرة يعني.
No, they continued keeping sheep, but not in large numbers.
يعني اللي كان عنده مثلاً 200، 300، 400 راس، صار يحوي له
مثلاً 20، 30 راس أخي.
I mean, whoever had 200, 300, or 400 heads of sheep, started
keeping 20 or 30 heads, brother.
نحن ما بنحسن نعيش بلا لبن وبلا جبن، ما بنحسن نعيش.
We cannot live without yogurt and without cheese, we can't
live.
ظلت يعني مشان أخي مونة البيت، وبنعيش أخي من هاللبن ومن
هالجبن والحليب.
They kept them for the house's pantry, and we live off this
yogurt, cheese, and milk.
هلق ضيعتكم كوكبة فيها 150 بيت، كم راس غنم فيها؟
Now, your village Kawkaba has 150 houses, how many heads of
sheep are in it?
والله هلق كثرنا.
By God, now we have increased them.
لأنه صار عنا أراضي وصرنا أخي مثلاً نزرع لهالغنم ونعطيها.
Because we got lands and started planting crops for these
sheep to feed them.
في شي حوالي الـ 2000 راس.
There are around 2000 heads.
2000 راس. إذاً بيئة حياتكم مرتبطة بالغنم، ولكن المصدر الدخل
الأساسي الكم ايش هو؟
2000 heads. So the environment of your life is tied to
sheep, but what is your primary source of income?
الزراعة، الزيتون والأرض.
Agriculture, olives, and the land.
طيب عمي أبو محمود، أنا ملاحظ هلق خلفي هيدي قناة المي.
Well, uncle Abu Mahmoud, I notice now behind me this water
canal.
هاي القناة جاية من سد ميدانكي؟
Is this canal coming from the Midanki Dam?
من سد ميدانكي.
From the Midanki Dam.
كأنه انتو سكنتوا الأماكن العالية اللي فيها مغر وفيها مراعي
وقريبة من المياه.
It seems you settled in the high places that have caves and
pastures, and are close to water.
نعم.
Yes.
قديش من هون بعيد مجرى نهر عفرين؟
How far is the course of the Afrin River from here?
والله يعني شي كيلو ونص متر.
By God, it's about a kilometer and a half.
بأي اتجاه؟
In which direction?
باتجاه أخي الـ... يعني الشرق.
In the direction of... the east.
باتجاه عفرين. بالعادي حيواناتكم بيسرحوا هنيك؟
Towards Afrin. Do your animals usually graze there?
نحن مرعى، يعني الغنم أخي أيام اللي ما في شي بتنزل عالنهر
بتسرح على نهر عفرين.
We use it as pasture, I mean on days when there is nothing,
the sheep go down to the river and graze by the Afrin River.
الله يعطيك العافية، ألف شكر إلك.
May God give you health, a thousand thanks to you.
الله يسلمك أهلين بالأستاذ، شرفتوا والله.
May God keep you safe, welcome sir, you've honored us by
God.
الله يكرمك.
May God bless you.
أهلين وسهلين.
You are very welcome.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
شلونك يا أمي؟
How are you, mother?
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
شلون صحتك؟
How is your health?
الحمد لله.
Praise be to God.
نتعرف عليكي؟
May we know your name?
عليا المحمد.
Aliya Al-Mohammad.
يا أهلاً وسهلاً فيكي.
You are very welcome here.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
من الضيعة من هون؟
Are you from this village?
اي من كوكبة.
Yes, from Kawkaba.
ايش في عندك فأس هي؟ ايش عم تساوي كنتي هيك؟
What is this hoe you have? What were you doing?
بدنا نروح نعفش الزيتونات.
We want to go gather the leftovers from the olive trees.
من هلق؟
From now?
اي لا الصبح يعني، جيت مريت وجيت قعدت هين.
Yes, well in the morning I mean, I came by and sat here.
بركتي هون ارتحتي.
You sat here and rested.
اي استراحيت.
Yes, I rested.
ايش قد عندك زيتونات؟
How many olive trees do you have?
والله عندي شي 30 شجرة.
By God, I have about 30 trees.
زوجك وينه؟
Where is your husband?
جوزي مات.
My husband died.
الله يرحمه، عندك أولاد؟
May God have mercy on him. Do you have children?
بنية بتركيا.
A daughter in Turkey.
فقط لحالك عايشة هون؟
Are you living here all alone?
اي والله، لحالي حوالي أهلي.
Yes, by God, alone, around my family.
احكيلي عن وضع المرأة هون، شلون؟
Tell me about the situation of women here, how is it?
والله المرأة عادي، تشتغل فلاحة.
By God, women's situation is normal, they work in farming.
مثلها مثل الرجل؟
Just like men?
ايوا.
Yes.
بتتعلم بالمدرسة؟
Do they study in school?
والله الصغار يتعلمن، وبيه منهن يتخرجن صارن آنسات.
By God, the young ones learn, and some of them graduate and
become teachers.
وجيلكم انتو؟
And your generation?
جيلنا لا.
Our generation, no.
جيلكم اشتغل بالزراعة بس.
Your generation only worked in agriculture.
ايوا.
Yes.
احكيلي عن لباس المرأة هون، عاداتكم تقاليدكم.
Tell me about women's clothing here, your customs and
traditions.
والله تقاليدنا يلبسن، بيه منهن بنطلونات، يلبسن جلابيات،
يلبسن أشكال الوان، تنورات شبونات.
By God, our traditions, they wear... some wear pants, they
wear galabiyas, they wear all sorts of things and colors,
skirts and dresses.
ايش الأكلات اللي عندكم هون بالضيعة؟ تحكيلي عنها؟ ايش تطبخوا؟
What are the dishes you have here in the village? Can you
tell me about them? What do you cook?
أكثر شي هالخضرة يعني، الباذنجان البطاطا.
Mostly these vegetables I mean, eggplants, potatoes.
لا الأكلات اللي بتفتخروا فيها، بتساووها هيك بالأعراس بالكذا.
No, the dishes you are proud of, the ones you make at
weddings and such.
اي لحم الطبخ، ولحم، وطبخ.
Oh, cooking meat, meat and cooked meals.
وشو كبة ما كبة؟
And what about Kibbeh and things like that?
كبة لا، بس لحم وطبخ ومناسف.
No Kibbeh, just meat, cooked meals, and Mansaf.
ايوا المناسف.
I see, Mansaf.
طيب تمام. احكيلي عن وضع المرأة هون بهالضيعة بكوكبة.
Alright, good. Tell me about the status of women here in
this village, in Kawkaba.
المرأة، يعني نص... يعني، مو بحيل مظلومة ولا مو مظلومة.
Women are, I mean, half... I mean, they are not heavily
oppressed, nor are they unoppressed.
شلون يعني؟
How do you mean?
يعني، عايشة ومستورة الحال.
I mean, she lives and her situation is decent.
دورها في المجتمع شلون؟ دورها، إلها دور في إصدار القرارات
المهمة في بيتها مثلاً؟
How is her role in society? Does she have a role in making
important decisions in her house, for example?
يعني إلها كلمة؟
You mean, does she have a say?
اي.
Yes.
اي يعني بيه منهن حاكمات، بيه منهن عاديات.
Yes, I mean, some of them are rulers of their homes, and
some are just regular.
الله يقويكي يا رب. ضيعة حلوة مو؟
May God give you strength. It's a beautiful village, right?
كوكبة أم الدنيا.
Kawkaba is the mother of the world.
أم الدنيا.
The mother of the world.
سوريا أم هاي الدنيا.
Syria is the mother of this world.
أحلى شي بهالضيعة ايش هو؟
What is the most beautiful thing in this village?
والله الزيتون، الزيتون.
By God, the olives, the olives.
الله يعطيكي العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
May God grant you health too.
شكراً إلك.
Thank you.
الله يعافيك أهلاً وسهلاً.
May God give you health, you're welcome.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام. أهلاً وسهلاً.
And upon you be peace. Welcome.
شلونكم؟
How are you?
تمام.
Great.
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Hello, Hajj.
Welcome.
وين كنت هيك انت والحجة؟
Where were you like this, you and the Hajja?
والله كنا نشبك بالشغل.
By God, we were busy working.
ما شاء الله، شو عم تشتغلوا؟
Mashallah, what are you working on?
والله كل واحد وظيفته، الفواكه، الزيتون.
By God, each has their duty, fruits, olives.
كنتوا بالكرم يعني بالبستان؟
You were in the orchard, I mean in the garden?
ايوا.
Yes.
انت اشتغلت بالزيتون ولا بالفواكه؟
Did you work with the olives or the fruits?
الزيتون والفواكه نفس الشيء، مزروعات سوا.
Olives and fruits are the same thing, they are planted
together.
كم شجرة عندك؟
How many trees do you have?
بي حوالي الـ 100، شجرة 200.
There are around 100, 200 trees.
100، 200.
100, 200.
ايوا.
Yes.
ايش في عندك أولاد؟
Do you have children?
واحد.
One.
وينه؟
Where is he?
هالحز هو بـ شو اسمها..
Right now he is in... what's it called...
وين؟
Where?
فوق بـ شو اسمها..
Up there in... what's it called...
باسوطة؟ عين دارة؟
Basouta? Ain Dara?
لا، باسوطة.
No, Basouta.
يعدي بغير شارع.
He should pass through another street.
يعني هلق انتوا من الصبح لهلق بالشغل؟
So you've been working from the morning until now?
من الصبح لهلق انصرفنا.
From the morning until now, we just finished.
ايش شايلين؟
What are you carrying?
والله شايلين البارحة حوشنا هالخضرة، وخلونا هذنه، جايبينهن
نطبخ هذنه.
By God, we are carrying... yesterday we picked these
vegetables, and they left us these, we brought them to cook
them.
مين اللي حوش الخضرة؟
Who picked the vegetables?
معلميتنا.
Our employers.
انت عم تشتغل عامل يعني؟
You are working as a laborer then?
يلا.
Yeah.
عند مين عم تشتغل؟
Who are you working for?
عند حاج كربوج، بيت كربوج.
For Hajj Karbouj, the Karbouj family.
مو كربوج العالي، كربوج العادي.
Not the upper Karbouj, the regular Karbouj.
يعني هلق انت ما عندك أرض؟
So right now you don't have land?
عندنا بس ما عندنا نقدر ننصب. ولا كل شي عندنا قاع وعندنا ارض
وعندنا حواش.
We do, but we can't afford to plant. Otherwise, we have
everything, a plot, land, and a yard.
الله يقويك.
May God give you strength.
سلامتك.
Peace to you.
الله يعطيكم العافية. الحجة مرتك مو هيك؟
May God give you both health. The Hajja is your wife, isn't
she?
ايوا.
Yes.
يلا الله يقويكم.
Alright, may God give you strength.
الله يسلمكم، أهلاً وسهلاً معاكم.
May God keep you safe, you are very welcome.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
وين ماشيين؟ جاي لعندكم.
Where are you walking to? I'm coming to you.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك. شلونك؟
May God grant you health too. How are you?
الحمد لله.
Praise be to God.
شلونك عمي؟
How are you, uncle?
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
لا تصير نحن نصورك مو انت بدك تصورنا.
Don't let it be that we film you, not you filming us.
لا بس خلينا نشوف حالي أول شي إذا مو ضابط لا تجيب الكاميرا
قدامنا.
No, but let me check how I look first; if it's not good,
don't bring the camera in front of us.
مرحبا مختار شلونك.
Hello Mukhtar, how are you?
مرحبتين.
Hello.
شلونك؟
How are you?
الحمد لله.
Praise be to God.
مزارع الفستق الأول.
The number one pistachio farmer.
ايه الحمد لله.
Yes, praise be to God.
وين الفستق تبعك؟ فرجيني.
Where are your pistachios? Show me.
الفستق والله زرعناه بين الزيتون.
By God, we planted the pistachios between the olive trees.
ايه.
Yes.
والله يعني ما لقينا أراضي سليخ، بتعرف إحنا نازحين من ريف
الجنوبي، وأخذنا بين الزيتون.
By God, we couldn't find empty lands. You know we are
displaced from the southern countryside, so we took land
between the olives.
تمام.
Okay.
وصاير تكلفة على المزارع بالحيل يعني.
And it's becoming very costly for the farmer.
تمام.
Right.
يعني بالنسبة لسماد وبالنسبة لمصروف، فعالة وما فعالة ومحروقات
ومازوت وغيره وغيراته.
I mean, regarding fertilizers and expenses, laborers and
non-laborers, fuels, diesel, and all the rest.
ايه والله زرعنا بين الزيتون.
Yes, by God, we planted between the olives.
كم زارع؟
How much did you plant?
والله زارع 16 دونم.
By God, I planted 16 dunams.
شلون يعني بينجح هون الفستق؟
How is it, do pistachios succeed here?
والله أراضي هين طيبة عندهم.
By God, the lands here are good.
ايه.
Yes.
بالنسبة لكوكبة أراضيهم طيبة، بس عاد قلة مواد بدها أسمدة وما
أسمدة.
As for Kawkaba, their lands are good, but there's a lack of
materials; it needs fertilizers and such.
المي من وين هاي؟
Where is this water from?
هاي مي من المشروع.
This is water from the project.
يعني من القناة.
You mean from the canal.
من القناة.
From the canal.
ايش جبتوا معكم انتوا، انت من وين حضرتك قلت لي؟
What did you bring with you? Where did you tell me you are
from?
أنا من ريف حلب الجنوبي، من الزربة.
I am from the southern countryside of Aleppo, from Al-
Zirbah.
من الزربة. وايش في نقلتوا هون غير زراعة الفستق؟ ايش زراعات
جديدة يعني نقلتوها معكم؟
From Al-Zirbah. And what did you transfer here other than
pistachio farming? What new crops did you bring with you?
والله إحنا زرعنا صويا، فول صويا هين بهاي الأرض.
By God, we planted soy, soybeans here in this land.
وزرعنا قتة.
And we planted Armenian cucumbers.
قتة، ايوا.
Armenian cucumbers, yes.
وهيدا الفستق، عم نتسلى يعني.
And these pistachios, we are just passing the time, I mean.
وكأنه كمان شايف هون سمسم.
It looks like I also see sesame here.
ايه هذا سمسم زرعنا سمسم.
Yes, this is sesame, we planted sesame.
سمسم، كمان نجح ان شاء الله؟
Sesame, did it succeed too, God willing?
والله يعني ماشي الحال، الحمد لله.
By God, it's doing alright, praise be to God.
الحمد لله.
Praise be to God.
مختار احكيلي عن الزراعة هون، نمشي هيك شوي لهون.
Mukhtar, tell me about agriculture here, let's walk a little
bit this way.
احكيلي عن الزراعة شوي بالضيعة.
Tell me a little about agriculture in the village.
والله الحمد لله، زراعة كوكبة من الزراعات الناجحة...
By God, praise be to God, agriculture in Kawkaba is among
the successful ones...
بالمنطقة وخاصة عندنا الزيتون...
In the region, and especially we have olives...
الزيتون.
Olives.
الزيتون من الأشجار المثمرة والحمد لله يعني زراعته ما له
تكلفة زيادة
Olives are fruitful trees, and thank God, planting them
doesn't cost much.
وإنتاجه عالي، والحمد لله بس إحنا ناقصنا مواد زراعية.
And its production is high. Thank God, we only lack
agricultural materials.
كم شجرة زيتون عندكم بالضيعة؟
How many olive trees do you have in the village?
عندنا تقريباً بالضيعة فوق الـ 100 ألف شجرة زيتون.
We have approximately over 100,000 olive trees in the
village.
ما شاء الله.
Mashallah.
غير الزيتون شو في عندكم؟
What else do you have besides olives?
عندنا حبة البركة، هي تشتهر كوكبة بحبة البركة.
We have black seed; Kawkaba is famous for black seed.
هي من جديد؟
Is this new?
هي من جديد زرعناها، والحمد لله إنتاجها كويس.
We planted it recently, and thank God, its production is
good.
ومحصولها كويس وأسعارها فادت المزارعين.
Its harvest is good, and its prices have benefited the
farmers.
ما شاء الله، خلينا نبرم هيك بالعكس، نشوف المشاهد..
Mashallah, let's turn around like this so the viewer can
see...
هالـ.. شو اسمها، القتة هيدي؟
This... what is it called, this Armenian cucumber?
القتة إي.
Armenian cucumber, yes.
أرض القتة الواسعة.
The vast field of Armenian cucumber.
إي.
Yes.
وهي زارعين هلق بعد موسم ثاني.
And these are planted now for a second season.
بعد حبة البركة زرعنا موسم ثاني، هي القتة.
After the black seed, we planted a second season, which is
the Armenian cucumber.
والحمد لله إنتاجها كويس واشتغلت كويس.
And thank God, its production is good and it worked out
well.
هلق القتة وحبة البركة، هنن بالأصل كنتوا تزرعوهم هون؟
Now, the Armenian cucumber and black seed, did you
originally plant them here?
ولا هيدا شيء مزروعات وافدة مع المهجرين؟
Or are these crops brought in by the displaced people?
لا، أجونا المهجرين جابونا زراعة الفستق،
No, the displaced people came and brought us pistachio
farming,
والعصفر، هذول الزراعات اللي كنا إحنا ما نعرفهم.
and safflower. These are crops we didn't know about.
بعد ما أجوا إخوتنا المهجرين من ريف حلب، من ريف إدلب، جابولنا
زراعات حديثة.
After our displaced brothers from the countryside of Aleppo
and Idlib arrived, they brought us modern crops.
أما هيدي، أما هيدي كانت..
But this one, this one was...
بس هي زراعتنا إحنا أباً عن جد، زراعة القتة والزيتون
والمحاصيل.
But this is our farming passed down from our ancestors,
growing Armenian cucumber, olives, and other crops.
بس زراعة الفستق والعصفر وهذول جابوهن الأخوة المهجرين
But growing pistachios, safflower, and such, the displaced
brothers brought them.
من ريف حلب وهيك.
From the countryside of Aleppo and so on.
شقد مساحة، شقد نسبة الأراضي اللي استثمروها المهجرين
What's the area, what's the percentage of lands invested by
the displaced people
بين الزيتون صاروا يزرعوها هي الزراعة التكثيفية؟
that they started farming between the olive trees with this
intensive agriculture?
والله إحنا ما كنا نزرع بين الزيتون، من أجونا الأخوة المهجرين
فادونا.
Well, we didn't use to plant between the olive trees until
the displaced brothers came and benefited us.
يعني بعد ما زرعوا بين الزيتون، تقريباً..
I mean, after they planted between the olives,
approximately...
100.. ما بدي أقول لك، 90% استفادينا بين الزياتين كلها.
100... I don't want to say that, 90% of all the areas
between the olive trees were utilized.
وفاد حتى الزيتون، أشجار الزيتون استفادت.
And it even benefited the olives; the olive trees benefited.
يعني 90% من المساحات اللي عندكم عم يزرعوها؟
So 90% of the lands you have are being planted?
مزروعة كلها من بين.. من فستق، من حبة بركة، من كل شيء.
They are entirely planted in between... with pistachios,
black seed, and everything.
وهذا نمط زراعي جديد عندكم؟
And is this a new agricultural pattern for you?
هذا نمط زراعي جديد. إحنا أولي زراعتنا معروفة؛ القمح، الحنطة،
الشعير.
This is a new agricultural pattern. Our early agriculture is
known: wheat, grain, barley.
الخضروات عندكم؟
And vegetables?
الخضروات، الزيتون، هاي زراعتنا. بعد ما أجونا الأخوة
المهجرين،
Vegetables, olives... this was our farming. After the
displaced brothers came to us,
يعني فادوا المنطقة، الحمد لله رب العالمين.
I mean, they benefited the region, praise be to God.
الله يعطيكم العافية ويرزقكم ويرزقهم.
May God give you strength, and provide for you and for them.
الله يعافيكم، الله يوفقكم ويخليكم، ونشكركم.
May God give you health, may God grant you success, keep you
safe, and we thank you.
على راسي يا أستاذ، الله يوفقك.
You're welcome, sir. May God grant you success.
تسلم، على راسي، تسلم.
Thank you, you're welcome, thank you.
[موسيقى]
[Music plays]
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
أهلين وسهلين.
Welcome.
شلونك حجي؟
How are you, Hajji?
أهلين وسهلين، الله يحييك. شلون صحتك؟
Welcome, may God greet you. How is your health?
الله يعافيك، أهلين وسهلين.
May God give you health, welcome.
ما شاء الله، عندك هون خيم ومحارة؟
Mashallah, you have tents and an encampment here?
إي والله، الحمد لله رب العالمين.
Yes indeed, praise be to God, Lord of the worlds.
حضرتك من وين؟
Where are you from?
أنا ريف حلب الجنوبي.
I'm from the southern countryside of Aleppo.
من وين بالضبط؟
From where exactly?
من شرق أبو الظهور، ضيعة اسمها جفرية.
From east of Abu Al-Duhur, a village called Jafriyah.
يا أهلاً وسهلاً فيك.
You are very welcome.
أهلين وسهلين بك.
Welcome to you too.
قديش صار لك هون؟ خلينا نمشي شوي لهون.
How long have you been here? Let's walk this way a bit.
والله صار لي تقريباً ثلاث سنين.
Well, I've been here for about three years.
ثلاث سنين؟
Three years?
إي والله.
Yes indeed.
ساكن هون بكوكبة؟
Living here in Kawkaba?
إي بكوكبة إي والله.
Yes, in Kawkaba, yes indeed.
مستأجر الأرض ولا شو مفصلها؟
Did you rent the land or how did you arrange it?
لا والله من جيراننا، عاطينا إياها هيك يعني، باركين فيها نعم.
No, well, from our neighbors. They gave it to us just like
that, and we are staying on it, yes.
كيف عايشين؟ شو في أسرتك؟ كم واحد؟
How are you living? What about your family? How many people?
والله أسرتي كبيرة.
Well, my family is large.
شقد يعني؟
How many, exactly?
أسرتي شي 30 شخص.
My family is about 30 people.
ما شاء الله! خلينا نقرب لقدام شوي. كم ولد عندك؟
Mashallah! Let's step forward a bit. How many children do
you have?
عندي 27 ولد.
I have 27 children.
ما شاء الله، اللهم صل على النبي. كم زوجة؟
Mashallah, peace be upon the Prophet. How many wives?
أربع زوجات.
Four wives.
كلهم عندك حالياً؟
Are they all with you currently?
عندي ثلاثة.
I have three.
والرابعة؟
And the fourth?
الرابعة مدثرها من زمان، دفنتها إي.
The fourth, I buried her a long time ago. I buried her, yes.
الله يسامحك.
May God forgive her.
أهلين بيك، أهلين وسهلين.
Welcome to you, welcome.
أهلاً بالحجي.
Welcome, Hajji.
أهلين وسهلين بيك.
Welcome to you.
يعني هلق هون محل ما لك بارك هون؟
So now, is this the place where you stay?
إي نعم.
Yes, indeed.
وهيك مشعل النار ومشغل كذا..
And you've lit a fire and such...
إي شو بدك الدنيا تعرف إنت، بهالجو هاد أخي، نبرك هيك برا أخي.
Yes, what do you want? You know the world. In this weather,
brother, we sit outside like this, brother.
على إيش عايشين هون؟ شو مصدر دخلكم؟
What do you live on here? What is your source of income?
والله عندنا هالغنمات.
Well, we have these sheep.
كم غنمة عندك؟
How many sheep do you have?
والله شي 40-50 غنمة، عايشين منهن، لا شغلة ولا عملة.
Well, about 40-50 sheep. We live off of them, no other job
or work.
ما بتاخذوا أراضي؟ ما بتشتغلوا في الأراضي؟
You don't take lands? You don't work in the fields?
لا والله، شغلتنا بالغنم بس.
No, well, our work is only with the sheep.
بس بالغنم؟
Just with the sheep?
إي والله.
Yes indeed.
طيب شو بيساووا الـ 40-50 غنمة لـ..
Well, what can 40-50 sheep do for...
لـ 30-40 نفس؟
For 30-40 people?
والله هاد هو، كلهم عندي، تعرف إنت اللي بتركيا، واللي بلبنان،
واللي عم يشتغل، أخي..
Well, that's it, they are all with me. You know, some are in
Turkey, some in Lebanon, and some are working, brother...
هلق إنت عندك 27، قلت لي شاب وبنت؟
Now, you have 27, you told me, boys and girls?
إي شاب وبنت.
Yes, boys and girls.
كم شاب؟
How many boys?
14 شاب.
14 boys.
و 13 بنت؟
And 13 girls?
و 13 بنت.
And 13 girls.
كم واحد متزوج منهم؟
How many of them are married?
متزوجة 12 بنت.
12 girls are married.
والشباب؟
And the boys?
الشباب والله، إذا قلت لك كم واحد متزوج، ما بتعرف!
The boys, well, if I told you how many are married, you
wouldn't know!
لا والله!
No way!
كم واحد معك؟
How many are with you?
معي هلق هون أربعة.
I currently have four here.
أربعة.
Four.
إي.
Yes.
وكم حفيد عندك؟
And how many grandchildren do you have?
إذا قلت لك ما بعرفهم! والله فوق الـ.. ما بعرف شقد، 150، ما
بعرف شقد، 200..
If I told you, I wouldn't know them! By God, over... I don't
know how many, 150, I don't know how many, 200...
والله صدقني ما بعرف شقد واحد.
I swear, believe me, I don't know how many people.
تعا تعا، إنت، إنت، إنت ابن ولا..؟ خليك خليك حجي، شرف لهون.
Come here, come here, you, you, are you his son or...? Stay,
stay, Hajji. Please come here.
لا خليك خليك.
No, stay, stay.
إنت ابنه ولا حفيده؟
Are you his son or his grandson?
ابنه.
His son.
ابنه؟ شو قد رقمك إنت، بتعرف؟
His son? What number are you, do you know?
ها؟
Huh?
شو قد رقمك عند الحجي؟ شقد ترتيبك؟
What's your number with Hajji? What is your order?
شو معرفني!
How should I know!
27؟
27?
لا هذا شي.. لا إي، أصغر، إي اثنين أصغر من هذولك، الجوز
الثنتين هذولك.
No, this one is... yes, younger, two are younger than those,
those two pair.
جوز جوز؟
Two of them?
إيوا.
Yes.
الحجة هيدي زوجتك؟
Hajja, is this your wife?
نعم.
Yes.
هيدي الرابعة؟
Is this the fourth?
هي الرابعة، ما شاء الله عليك يا حجي.
This is the fourth. Mashallah, Hajji.
أهين وسهلين.
Welcome.
الله يقويك يا رب. شو شفت لي بهالحياة إنت بعد هيك..
May God give you strength. What have you seen in this life
after such...
أربع زوجات، و 27 ما شاء الله شاب وبنت، وعدد كبير ما شاء الله
من الأحفاد..
Four wives, and 27 boys and girls, Mashallah, and a large
number of grandchildren, Mashallah...
شو شفت لي بهالحياة؟
What have you seen in this life?
شفت؟
What have I seen?
إي بهالحياة إي، شو، شو اللي استخلصته؟
Yes, in this life, yes. What, what have you concluded?
والله حياة عدت علينا أشكال ألوان وعجايب الزمان، مشكل ملون
تعرف إنت الحياة أخي..
Well, a life has passed us by with all shapes, colors, and
wonders of time, mixed and colorful. You know life,
brother...
قاسية، فيها هيك وفيها هيك، فيها حلوة وفيها مرة.
It's harsh, it has its ups and downs, it has sweet and
bitter moments.
والله يرجعنا على بلادنا، غير هيك ما في.
And may God return us to our lands, there is nothing other
than that.
آمين. خليني أحكي مع الحجة طالما إجت، معلش.
Amen. Let me talk to Hajja since she came, if you don't
mind.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
الحمد لله شلونك؟
Thank God. How are you?
الحمد لله بخير شلونك؟
Thank God, I'm well. How are you?
الحمد لله، هذول أولادك؟
Thank God. Are these your children?
إي.
Yes.
شو أسماءهم؟
What are their names?
يحيى، وزكريا.
Yahya, and Zakaria.
يحيى وزكريا.
Yahya and Zakaria.
إي.
Yes.
الله يخليكم إياهم.
May God protect them for you.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
بتشتغلي مع الحجي بالـ.. بتربية الحيوانات؟
Do you work with Hajji in... in raising animals?
إي نساعده بالـ.. كل شي نساعده إي.
Yes, we help him in... we help him with everything, yes.
وين أهلك؟
Where is your family?
هين زاد أهلي بكوكبة.
My family is also here in Kawkaba.
كمان؟
Also here?
إي.
Yes.
شلون هالضيعة؟
How is this village?
كويسة.
Good.
الناس معاشرانيين، بيساعدوا بعضهم؟
Are the people sociable, do they help each other?
إي والله جخة الحمد لله، ما شفنا غير الخير منهم.
Yes, by God, great, praise be to God. We've seen nothing but
good from them.
الله يرزقكم يا رب ويعطيكم العافية.
May God provide for you and give you strength.
الله يسلمك يا رب.
May God keep you safe.
على راسي يا حجي.
You're welcome, Hajji.
أهلين وسهلين.
Welcome.
عمي أبو إيش؟
Uncle Abu what?
أبو محمد.
Abu Muhammad.
على راسي يا عمي أبو محمد.
You're welcome, Uncle Abu Muhammad.
معيوف الجاسم أبو محمد.
Ma'youf Al-Jassim Abu Muhammad.
على راسي، على راسي، على راسي.. الله يكرمكم.
You're welcome, you're welcome, you're welcome... May God
honor you.
الله يحفظكم.
May God protect you.
تفضلوا، خلينا نتعشى، صار وقت العشاء.
Please, let's have dinner, it's dinner time.
والله.. والله لنتعشى، والله إنت بتكرم.
By God... By God, we will have dinner. By God, you are
generous.
العيش مخبور، مو هيك العرب؟
Bread is shared, isn't that the way of the Arabs?
الله يكرمك، الله يكرمك.
May God honor you, may God honor you.
أهلين وسهلين.
Welcome.
أعزائي المشاهدين، انتهت هذه الجولة الجميلة من قرية كوكبة في
ريف عفرين الغربي الجنوبي.
Dear viewers, this beautiful tour of the village of Kawkaba
in the southwestern countryside of Afrin has come to an end.
سنكون معكم في الأسابيع القادمة في جولة جديدة من مناطق سورية
أخرى حبيبة.
We will be with you in the coming weeks on a new tour of
other beloved Syrian regions.
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.
[موسيقى]
[Music plays]